Guide to the Love Makes a Family Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Love Makes a Family records
1991-2010
MS 1962
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
20.25
(49 boxes and approximately 36 gigabytes)
The Love Makes a Family (LMF) records consist of email correspondence, bylaws, reports, meeting minutes, research data, publications, Web pages, social media account files, topical files, interviews and testimonies, photographs, audiovisual recordings, and newspaper clippings documenting the history, structure, and activities of LMF, Inc. and its related organizations, the LMF Political Action Committee (PAC) and the LMF Foundation. LMF's principal goals were to pass a second-parent adoption law; support efforts to pass a domestic partnership package for state employees; defeat Defense of Marriage Amendments (DOMAs) both to the state statute and the state constitution; and pass a marriage equality law for same-sex couples in Connecticut. As the first three goals were reached by 2000, the records primarily document LMF's efforts on behalf of marriage equality.
Love Makes a Family, Incorporated
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Love Makes a Family, 2009 and 2010.
Scope and Contents
The Love Makes a Family (LMF) records consist of email correspondence, bylaws, reports, meeting minutes, research data, publications, Web pages, social media account files, topical files, interviews and testimonies, photographs, audiovisual recordings, and newspaper clippings documenting the history, structure, and activities of LMF, Inc. and its related organizations, the LMF Political Action Committee (PAC) and the LMF Foundation. The records are comprised primarily of the records maintained by Anne Stanback (president and executive director) and Carol Buckheit (associate director and executive director) and document all aspects of the organization including executive administration, strategy and policy development, fundraising, education and advocacy efforts, communications, and relationships to other marriage equailty organizations. As LMF reached its first three goals in its first year, the vast majority of the records document the effort to legalize same-sex marriage. The records document all the major developments of the marriage equality movement in Connecticut, as well as the broader national movement and its opposition. Additionally individual lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgendered persons' lives and the impact of marriage discrimination is richly documented in testimonials, public hearing statements, and interviews. To a lesser extent other lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgender anti-discrimination efforts in the state are also documented.
Conditions Governing Access
Series I, Box 20 is closed to research until January 1, 2025. Box 21 requires written permission to access from the Love Makes a Family trustees until January 1, 2025, after which they are open to research.
Arrangement
The records are arranged in three series: I. Administrative Records,1991-2010. II. Audiovisual Recordings and Photographs, 2000-2009. III. Website and Social Media Sites, 2009-2010.
Biographical / Historical
Love Makes a Family (LMF) (1999-2009) was a Connecticut statewide coalition of organizations and individuals whose mission was to pass a second-parent adoption law; support efforts to pass a domestic partnership package for state employees; defeat Defense of Marriage Amendments (DOMAs) both to the state statute and the state constitution; and to pass a marriage equality law for same-sex couples in Connecticut. The first three goals were reached by 2000; the marriage equality law was passed in 2008. In 2005, LMF joined a statewide coalition to end discrimination based on gender identity and expression, thereby adding transgender rights to its awareness and advocacy campaign. Passing a marriage bill, however, remained its primary focus. Love Makes a Family developed into three inter-related entities: LMF, Inc., incorporated as a 501(c)(4) in 2000; the LMF Political Action Committee (PAC), established in 2002; and the LMF Foundation, incorporated as a 501(c)(3) in 2006. After meeting its goals through community education, grassroots organizing, and legislative advocacy and lobbying, LMF, Inc. and LMF Foundation disbanded in 2009. The LMF PAC continues to work for lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgender equality in Connecticut by supporting and working for pro equality candidates for elected office.
In its first phase of work on second-parent adoption during 1999 and 2000, LMF Inc.'s informal Steering Committee was comprised of representatives from five statewide organizations: the American Civil Liberties Union of Connecticut, the Connecticut Coalition of LGBT Civil Rights, the Connecticut Conference of the United Church of Christ, the Connecticut State Permanent Commission on the Status of Women, and the Connecticut Women's Education and Legal Fund. Once LMF, Inc. began the process of organizational incorporation and refocused its mission on marriage equality, the Steering Committee expanded, consisting of a president, vice-president, secretary, treasurer; representatives from six regional chapters; and representatives from six statewide organizations (the Permanent Commission on the Status of Women stepped down and Parents, Friends and Families of Lesbians and Gays (PFLAG), True Colors and DemocracyWorks ultimately joined). This structure remained in place until 2006 when a more traditional Board of Directors structure was put in place. In 2006, the LMF Foundation was incorporated as a 501(c) (3) that was primarily run by a board of directors, an executive director, and an associate director. LMF, Inc. was originally run by volunteers but by 2008, it had grown to consist of several full and part-time staff, including administrators, field organizers, a lobbyist, a financial manager, an events coordinator, and a Web site designer. While the organization benefited from the efforts of many individuals, several stand out for their length of service: Anne Stanback served as president from 2000 to 2005 and executive director from 2006-2009; Betty Gallo served as lobbyist from 1999 to 2005 and 2007 to 2008; Alice Pritchard served in various roles from 2002 to 2008; Beverley Brakeman served as secretary from 2003 to 2007; Chelsea Turner served as a lobbyist from 2000 to 2004; and Carol Buckheit served in various roles, including associate director and executive director, respectively, from 2005 to 2009.
The organization accomplished its goals through community education, grassroots organizing, and legislative advocacy and lobbying. LMF volunteers and staff trained and organized community volunteers; gave presentations; organized community forums, rallies, and public hearings; canvassed voters; commissioned research; managed a speakers' bureau; served as a clearinghouse on civil union and marriage information; and lobbied legislators. LMF was recognized as a leader in the marriage equality movement. Anne Stanback and LMF were recognized with several honors, including Stanback's induction into the Connecticut Women's Hall of Fame.
Information in this organizational history is drawn from the Love Makes a Family Annual Report (2001-2008).
Gay couples -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- Connecticut; Same-sex marriage -- Law and legislation -- Connecticut; Transgender people -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- Connecticut; LGBTQ resource; Stanback, Anne; Love Makes a Family Foundation; Love Makes a Family Political Action Committee; Love Makes a Family, Incorporated
- Administrative Files, 1991-2010; Series I
  Arrangement
  Series I is arranged by administrative function.
  Scope and Contents
  The Administrative Records series is divided into seven sections: Executive Director's records, Associate Director's records, Field Organizer's records, Religious Organizer's records, Financial records, Printed material, and General resource files. The most substantive materials are found in the Executive Director's records, which document all aspects of the organization. For example, the organization's history can be gleaned from bylaws, board minutes, and annual reports. Lobbying, research, and advocacy activities pertaining to the same-sex marriage bill and same-sex marriage cases in various states can be found in the topical files under Legislative efforts. The Associate Director was primarily responsible for public relations and communications and, as such, records on those topics, including press releases and materials documenting fundraising events, are found in that section.
  The records of the Field and Religious organizers provide a glimpse of LMF's field and specialized campaigns to gain support for their legislative agenda. The Financial records consist of budgets, audits, and tax returns. Of special note in the Printed material section are newspaper clippings covering the same-sex marriage movement in Connecticut and LMF's role in it from 2002 to 2009 and the "Love Makes A Family: The LMF Testimonial Book" with personal statements from state residents. Materials in the General resource files are of a more general nature and did not belong to any one person at LMF.
  Many of the events documented in Series I are also documented in Series II, Audiovisual Recordings and Photographs. Researchers interested in a particular event should consult the listings for both series.
  - Executive Director
    - Email correspondence (electronic), Computer files.
      Conditions Governing Access
      Original computer files, as well as preservation masters, are restricted. Electronic files cannot be accessed remotely. Copies of the files are available in the repository.
      - 2005-2009 Lesgislative sessions
      - 2008 field report
      - 2009 Political Directors Meeting, 2009 May 19-20
      - Annual Report 2008, 2008-2009
      - Archives of LMF, 2009
      - Articles, 2004-2009
      - Betty Hudson early CT gay articles, 2009 September 23
      - Board emails (Steering Committee), 2005-2006
      - Board emails, 2007-2009
      - Bradway articles, 2006-2008
      - Con Con Press, 2008
      - CT Congressional DOMA efforts, 2009
        - Con Con 2008, 2007-2009
      - CT Organizations to profile at closure, 2009
      - Decision Day planning and logistics, 2007-2008
      - Eat, Drink, and Be Married (EDBM), 2008-2009
      - ENDA, 2009
      - Elections 2004-2008, 2004-2009
      - Equality Federation, 2005-2009
      - Executive Committee Emails, 2007-2009
      - Fatherhood Task Force 2008, 2008 September 18
      - FIC (Family Insititute of Connecticut), 2006-2010
      - Gay Parenting, 2004-2006
      - Gill Action, 2008
      - Interim Executive Director Information, 2008-2009
      - Legislator replies to Kerrigan email, 2008 October 16-30
      - LMF closure and transadvocacy, 2009 April
      - LMF emails to members, 2005-2009
      - LMF Foundation Board emails, 2005-2007
      - LMF stationery pdfs, 2005 December 7
      - Membership Organization issues, 2007-2008
      - National Organization for Marriage (NOM), 2007-2009
      - Polygamy arguments, 2006-2008
      - Quotes of note, 2005-2007
      - Religious organizing 2008-2009, 2009 May 19
      - Rep. Kim Fawcett, 2009
      - Rhode Island, 2009 May
      - Stamford event, 2007
      - Strategic planning for future of LMF, 2007-2009
      - Website Convio, 2005-2008
    - Topical files
      - Electronic, Computer files.
        - 2001 Marriage Forum, 2000-2001
        - 2004 Democratic Party Platform
        - 2005 LMF Decision on Civil Unions
        - 2006 Field Efforts, 2006 April 26
        - 2008-2009 Strategic Planning rCP-Catalyst Committee, 2008-2010
        - 2008 c3 board list, 2007
        - Anne E. Stanback photographs and biography, 2006-2009
        - Attorney General, 2004
        - Board and Closure
          - Accounts closed and dissolution plans, 2009
          - Archiving and database work, 2009
          - Board minutes, agendas and Executive Director reports 7.09-12.09, 2009
          - Deed of Gift and Trustee documents, 2009
          - Financial reports 7.09 to 12.09, 2009
          - Grant progress reports 7.09 to 12.09, 2009
          - Mini-grants to LGBT organizations, 2009
          - No on 1 Maine, 2009
          - Nov 12 1 year marriage anniversary event, 2009
        - Bradway Investigation, 2006
        - Business Leaders 2007
        - c4 board manual materials, 2008
        - Civil Union Stats, 2007 November 30
        - Community Works of CT, 2008-2010
        - Congressional Delegation correspondence, 2004-2009
        - Constitutional Convention 2008
        - CT Clergy for Marriage Equality (CCME), 2005
        - CTAC (Connecticut TransAdvocacy Coalition), 2008
        - Diversity efforts, 2004-2006
        - Electoral work c4, 2007-2008
        - Electronic letterhead c3 and c4, 2008-2009
        - Emails to members, Steering Committee, etc., 2003-2005, 2010
        - ENDA 2007
        - Ethics Commission, 2004 January 20
        - Ethics and Elections memos, 2007
        - Family Institute of CT, 2004 February 7
        - Federal Constitutional Amendment, 2003
        - Foundation 501c3, 2004-2008
        - Fundraising, 2002-2008
        - GLAD, 2005-2007
        - Goodridge v. MA, 2003-2004
        - Governor Rell, 2004-2007
        - Grassroots Organizing, 2007-2009
        - IGLSS Fiscal Impact Study, 2004-2005
        - Kerrigan v. CT, 2004-2010
        - Lawrence v. Texas Supreme Court Decision, 2003 June 26
        - Legislative Sessions, 2000-2009
        - LMF closing, 2009
        - LMF PAC, 2002-2008
        - Mayors for Marriage Equality, 2008 April
        - Messaging, 2004-2006
        - Miscellaneous correspondence, 2001-2008
        - News Articles, Op-eds, 2002-2007
        - Other States, Countries, Cities, 2002-2004
        - Planning 2007, 2006-2007
        - Polling, 2002-2007
        - Press Releases, etc., 2002-2008, 2001-2009
        - Primary LMF organizational and administrative information
          - Agendas, 2000-2009
          - Annual Reports, 2002-2009
          - Audit, 2006-2009
          - Board Resolutions and Policies, 2006-2009
          - Board-Staff Retreats, 2002-2004
          - DRS, 2004-2005
          - Executive Director Reports, 2006-2009
          - Foundation 501c3, 2005-2008
          - Incorporation & Structure, 2000-2007
          - Minutes, 2004-2009
          - Mission, 2008-2009
          - Office procedures 2008, 2008-2009
          - Personnel Policies, 2006-2007
        - Printed materials (fact sheets, brochures, stationery), 2001-2007
        - Rally for Marriage 5-16-04, 2004
        - Religious Organizing, 2001-2010
        - Second-Parent Adoption, 2002
        - Speakers Bureau, 2003-2010
        - Speackout 2-8-04, 2004
        - Speeches, Testimony, Op-eds, 2001-2009
        - Statements of support for legal briefs, 2008
        - Sub-lease, 2007
        - Supporting organizations, 2002-2010
        - Transgender organizing, 2008
        - Unions-Labor Support, 2004-2010
        - Victory Fund States Project, 2006 January 28
        - Voter ID Project, 2003-2005
      - Paper
        - General
          - Original LMF organizational documents, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 1)
            Invitational letter and overview of first meeting.
          - Allocation Agreement between 501c3 (c3) and 501c4 (c4), 2006-2009 (Box 1, Folder 2)
          - Board
            - Resolutions and policies, 2003-2008 (Box 1, Folder 3)
            - Executive Director/staff reports to board, 2006-2009 (Box 1, Folder 4)
            - Board and Executive Committee meeting agendas-joint c3 and c4 meetings, 2007-2009 (Box 1, Folder 5)
            - Meetings, 2008-2009 (Box 1, Folder 6-10)
            - Member agreements-c4, 2006-2008 (Box 1, Folder 11)
            - Member agreements-c3, 2006-2008 (Box 1, Folder 12)
          - 501c4 IRS application and determination letter, 2001-2007 (Box 1, Folder 13)
          - Bylaws for c4, 2005-2006 (Box 1, Folder 14)
          - Department of Labor filings-c4, 2007-2008 (Box 1, Folder 15)
          - Secretary of State corporate filings-c4, 2002-2008 (Box 1, Folder 16)
          - Census material, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 17)
          - Dept of Consumer Protection/Public Charities filings-c4, 2001-2009 (Box 1, Folder 18)
          - 990/Audit- c4, 2001-2008 (Box 2, Folder 1-8)
          - 501c3 IRS application and determination letter, 2002-2009 (Box 2, Folder 9)
          - Bylaws for c3 (LMF Foundation), 2005 (Box 2, Folder 10)
          - Secretary of the State corporate filings - c3, 2005-2009 (Box 2, Folder 11)
          - Office of State Ethics filings, 2005-2009 (Box 2, Folder 12)
          - Connecticut state tax info - c3, 2004-2006 (Box 2, Folder 13)
          - Dept. of Consumer Protection/Public Charities filings-c3, 2006-2009 (Box 2, Folder 14)
          - City of Hartford Property tax form - c3, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 15)
          - 990/Audit- c3, 2006-2008 (Box 2, Folder 16-18)
          - Legal info/general - c3 and c4, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 19)
          - Fiscal agent agreement - c4 and Connecticut Women's Education and Legal Fund, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 20)
          - Fiscal agreement - c3 and Connecticut TransAdvocacy Coalition, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 21)
          - Personnel policies for staff, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 22)
          - Non discrimination policy, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 23)
          - Lease documents at 576 Farmington Ave, 2006-2009 (Box 2, Folder 24)
          - Sub-lease with Zlokower & Miller, 2007-2009 (Box 2, Folder 25)
          - Lease documents at Grand Street, 2004-2006 (Box 2, Folder 26)
          - Annual Reports, 2000-2008 (Box 3, Folder 1)
          - Strategic Planning, 2007-2009 (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
            Includes planning documents related to LMF's decision to close.
            - Additional materials, 2006-2008 (Box 21, Folder 1-2)
              Written permission from Love Makes a Family trustees is required to access this material until January 1, 2025.
          - LMF grassroots organizing overview/history, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 4)
          - Mayors for Marriage Equality Project, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 5)
          - Marriage Equality Forum, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 6)
          - Letter to LMF Members regarding Michael Bradway, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 7)
          - Equality Federation, 2007-2009 (Box 3, Folder 8)
          - Democracy Project, 2005-2008 (Box 3, Folder 9)
          - NCCJ Diversity Training, 2005-2006 (Box 3, Folder 10)
          - 2004 Retreat (Box 3, Folder 11)
          - LMF structure, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 12)
          - Website, 2001-2004 (Box 3, Folder 13)
          - May 16, 2004 Marriage Rally (Box 3, Folder 14)
          - Latinos/as for Marriage Equality, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 15)
          - Speakout for Marriage Equality, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 16)
          - Voter ID Project, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 17)
          - African American/Civil Rights issues, Circa 2004 (Box 3, Folder 18)
          - Supporting organizations, 2000-2001 (Box 3, Folder 19)
          - Communications plan/branding, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 20)
          - Marriage Equality for Same Sex Marriage...: Speakers Bureau training, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
            - "Marriage Equality for Same Sex Couples: A Connecticut Conversation", Circa 2003
          - "Speaker's Training, L-A-R-A-AA Personal Story", 2005 (Box 4, Folder 3)
          - Retreat, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 1)
          - Religious Organizing/Clergy organizing (Box 5, Folder 2)
          - Transgender organizing, Circa 2002-2009 (Box 20, Folder 2)
            Restricted until January 1, 2025.
          - "Gay Rights Bill" religious support, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 3)
          - Sample activist packet, Circa 2003-2007 (Box 5, Folder 4)
          - Marriage Forum, 2001 January 30 (Box 5, Folder 5)
        - Legislative Efforts
          - Lobbyist Reports, 2001-2009 (Box 5, Folder 6)
            Detailed information on marriage effort from each legislative session.
          - Marriage Codification Bill; 2009 legislative session (Box 5, Folder 7)
          - 2007 Legislative session (Box 5, Folder 8)
          - 2007 Judiciary Committee marriage hearing (Box 5, Folder 9)
          - 2006 Legislative session (Box 5, Folder 10)
          - Task Force Benefits of Marriage Study, 2005 January (Box 5, Folder 11)
            National Gay and Lesbian Task Force study commissioned by LMF.
          - Institute for Gay and Lesbian Strategic Studies (IGLSS) Economic Impact Study, 2005 March (Box 5, Folder 12)
          - 2005 Lobby Day; Judiciary Committee public hearing, 2005 February (Box 5, Folder 13)
          - LMF testimony in Judiciary Committee Hearing; press release, 2005 February (Box 5, Folder 14)
          - Civil Union Bill, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 15)
          - Vote counts, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 16)
          - Message points, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 17)
          - Lobbying, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 18)
          - 2005 grassroots plan (draft) (Box 5, Folder 19)
          - 2004 legislative handouts (Box 5, Folder 20)
          - Governor Rell letter, 2004 December (Box 6, Folder 1)
          - Grassroots and political plan, 2004 (Box 6, Folder 2)
          - Proposed bills and amendments, 2003 (Box 6, Folder 3)
          - Judiciary Committee Public hearing; marriage testimony, 2003 February (Box 6, Folder 4)
          - Legislator handouts, 2003 (Box 6, Folder 5)
          - Press conference material, 2003 (Box 6, Folder 6)
          - Grassroots legislative information; post session, 2003 (Box 6, Folder 7)
          - Public Act 02-105, 2002 (Box 6, Folder 8)
            General
            Public Act 02-105 granted limited rights to same-sex couples.
          - 2002 Legislative session (Box 6, Folder 9)
          - Testimony (selected) from 2002 public hearing (Box 6, Folder 10)
          - 2002 legislative handouts (Box 6, Folder 11)
          - 2002 Lobby Day, 2002 April (Box 6, Folder 12)
          - 2002 clergy press conference, 2002 February (Box 6, Folder 13)
          - Press conference; response to Catholic petition drive, 2002 November (Box 6, Folder 14)
          - Judiciary Committee hearings, 2001-2002 (Box 6, Folder 15-18)
          - 2001 General organizing (Box 6, Folder 19)
          - Lobby day, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 1)
          - Fact sheets, 2001-2003 (Box 7, Folder 2)
          - Miscellaneous marriage testimony, 2002-2005 (Box 7, Folder 3-5)
          - 2000 miscellaneous (Box 7, Folder 6)
          - Transcripts of second-parent adoption testimony, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 7)
          - 1999/2000 legislative session; adoption and Domestic Partnership (Box 7, Folder 8)
          - Co-Parent adoption, 1999-2000 (Box 7, Folder 9)
          - Gender Identity and Expression legislation, 2006-2009 (Box 7, Folder 10)
            Consists of materials from the Transgender Anti-Discrimination Coalition.
          - State Employee Domestic Partnership benefits, 2008 (Box 7, Folder 11)
          - Vermont: Nancy Cott testimony on marriage, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 1)
          - Vermont Civil Union effort materials, 2000-2002 (Box 8, Folder 2)
          - California DP law (Domestic Partnership), Circa 2001 (Box 8, Folder 3)
          - Hawaii marriage, 1995 (Box 8, Folder 4)
          - Attorney General Blumenthal
            - Opinion on civil union, 2005 November (Box 8, Folder 5)
            - Letter to Massachusetts Governor Romney, 2004 May (Box 8, Folder 6)
            - LMF letter to Attorney General Blumenthal regarding marriage, 2004 March (Box 8, Folder 7)
          - Correspondence to Connecticut Congressional delegation, 2003-2009 (Box 8, Folder 8)
          - Miscellaneous opposition, 2000-2009 (Box 8, Folder 9)
            Includes materials from the Family Institute of Connecticut and the Catholic Conference.
            - The Family Institute of Connecticut Highlights 2003, 1